<?xml-stylesheet href="/rss.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>devashish.me</title>
    <link>https://devashish.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on devashish.me</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2025 Devashish Meena; All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 23:16:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://devashish.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>About</title>
        <link>https://devashish.me/about/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2024 23:16:31 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://devashish.me/about/</guid>
        <description>devashish.me https://devashish.me/about/ -&lt;p&gt;I am a seasoned technology leader with 15+ years of experience scaling engineering organizations,
driving product innovation, and aligning technology strategies with business goals.
Having worked with four early-stage startups, including two successful exits, I’ve honed my expertise
in building enterprise and consumer products from the ground up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My journey has been defined by leading distributed teams to deliver secure, scalable,
and high-growth products. With a primary focus on designing iterative application architectures,
I specialize in creating solutions that maximize value and enable organizations to deploy code faster
through automation-first approach. These processes have not only optimized developer productivity
but have also fostered team learning and cross-functional collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When not working, I enjoy cooking, reading, hiking, running, and riding my motorcycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimers&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All views expressed on this site are my own and do not represent the opinions of my employers or any other organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All images © 2024 Devashish Meena.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
- https://devashish.me/about/ - © 2025 Devashish Meena; All rights reserved</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Initial Commit</title>
        <link>https://devashish.me/posts/initial_commit/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 14:04:26 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://devashish.me/posts/initial_commit/</guid>
        <description>devashish.me https://devashish.me/posts/initial_commit/ -&lt;p&gt;For the V4 version of this blog, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to remove all the old entries and start
from scratch. With one significant change though: posting tech content only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time I&amp;rsquo;ve lost interest in writing travel blogs and inflicting my unfiltered
thoughts on public forums. At the same time, I&amp;rsquo;d started documenting my
experiences and learnings at work, conversations with other people in industry
and takeaways from reading up on the topics that excite me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I (re)started this blog with a few objectives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document my journey in building tech solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep notes about interesting concepts, their implementations and other aspects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have discussion(s) about the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to solve problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To new beginnings!&lt;/p&gt;
- https://devashish.me/posts/initial_commit/ - © 2025 Devashish Meena; All rights reserved</description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 